Finding Aid for Frederick G. Sampson papers, 1970-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Frederick G. Sampson papers 1970-2008
Sampson, Frederick G. (Frederick George), 1928-2001.
2010019 Aa 2
Church documents and personal papers of Dr. Frederick G. Sampson II, pastor of Tabernacle Missionary Baptist Church of Detroit Mich., noted lecturer and keynote speaker, and member of various commissions and boards dedicated to human rights, community outreach, and community education.
1.25 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Collection received from Freda G. Sampson, daughter of Frederick Sampson, in 2010 (donor no. 10305 ).
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Frederick G. Sampson II was born in Port Arthur, Texas on August 9, 1928 and started his career teaching mathematics in his hometown. His work as a Baptist minister began in Texarkana, Arkansas and eventually led him to the Tabernacle Missionary Baptist Church in Detroit, where he served from 1971 until his death in 2001.
Dr. Sampson earned numerous degrees: two bachelors from Bishop College; bachelor's and a master's degree from Howard University; and master's degrees from Columbus State University and the University of Louisville. He earned his doctoral degree from Virginia Theological Seminary and earned certificates and honorary degrees from several other colleges and universities. In 1984 and again in 1993 Ebony Magazine named Dr. Sampson one of the 15 Greatest Black Preachers in America.
Dr. Sampson lectured at colleges and universities across the country, conducted numerous yearly revivals, created study courses and other materials for the Baptists and for the YMCA, and broadcast regularly on the radio. His work included conducting conferences on black male spirituality, planning the 1965 voting rights march with Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., and serving as president of the Detroit branch of the NAACP.
The Frederick G. Sampson collection includes personal and church related papers that document his professional work and church activities from 1970 until his death in 2001. In addition, there is some information about the Foundation established in his name. The papers are arranged in the following series: Pastoral Career and Personal Papers.
Subjects:
African American churches--Michigan--Detroit.; African American clergy--Michigan--Detroit.; African American men--Conduct of life.; African American men--Michigan--Detroit.; African Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Baptists, Black--Michigan--Detroit.; Civil rights--Michigan--Detroit.; Clergy--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Detroit (Mich.)--Race relations.; Sampson, Frederick G. (Frederick George), 1928-2001.; Tabernacle Missionary Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Pastoral career
  The Pastoral Career series contains event programs, newsletters, souvenir books, and papers related to church procedures and policies during Dr. Sampson's career at the Tabernacle Missionary Baptist Church. Dr. Sampson conducted a yearly conference on the family and black male spirituality at Tabernacle, which drew about 1000 men and youths to the church each year. The programs, brochures, and publicity materials for African American Male Spirituality Week, from 1992 through 2001, are included. In addition, there are programs from Mount Lebanon Baptist Church in Louisville, Kentucky, where Dr. Sampson served as pastor from 1960-1971.
  - Mount Lebanon Baptist Church programs 1961-1969 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Tabernacle Missionary Baptist Church
    - History/Background
      - Church history 1990 (Box 1)
      - Anniversary booklet
        - 1981 (Box 1)
        - 1995 (Box 1)
      - Souvenir Book and program for dedication of new facilities 2005 (Box 1)
    - Events and services
      - Weekly church service programs 1996, 2000 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous church event flyers and brochures 1971-2000 (Box 1)
      - Charles Bolden Jr. project 1986 (Box 1)
      - African American Male Spirituality Week 1992-2001, 10 folders (Box 1)
      - Neighborhood block party 1992, 1994 (Box 1)
      - Sermon list 1977-1997 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Newsletters 1975-2000 (scattered) (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous documents (Box 1)
        (includes policies and procedures, and other miscellanea)
- Personal papers
  Dr. Sampson's Personal Papers contain: handwritten notes, writings, a book by Dr. Sampson, and other writings related to his work in the community. Biographical information includes newspaper clippings, photographs of church activities and individual portraits, funeral programs, and obituaries for Dr. Sampson and his wife. A copy of Dr. Sampson's book," The Romance of Theology in the Black Experience," 1980, is included.
  - Writings, sermons, speaking events
    - "The Romance of Theology in the Black Experience," by Dr. F. G. Sampson 1980 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 1)
    - Notes (Box 1)
    - WMUZ radio broadcast text 1997 (Box 1)
    - Speaking events, flyers and brochures
      - 1968-1995 (Box 1)
      - 1996-2001 (Box 1)
  - Biographical
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
    - Photographs (Box 1)
    - "Celebration of the Life Long God Strong Ministry" honoring Dr. Frederick Sampson II 1996 (Box 2)
      (includes programs, souvenir book, planning documents and other miscellanea)
    - Frederick G. Sampson Foundation (Box 2)
      (includes brochures for sponsored events and one audio CD)
    - Biographical information, funeral program, obituary
      - Frederick Sampson 2001 (Box 2)
      - Earlene Sampson 1996 (Box 2)
  - Resolutions from Michigan Civil Rights Commission 1983 and from the State of Michigan, 1994; also congratulatory document from the United States 104th Congress (Folder 1)